Finding Aid for Vice President and Chief Financial Officer (University of Michigan) Records, 1909-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Executive Vice President and Chief Financial Officer (University of Michigan) records
1909-2006
University of Michigan. Executive Vice-President and Chief Financial Officer.
87345 Bimu B6 2 Ac
Central administrative office responsible for financial management of the University of Michigan and fiscal policy with oversight for the general fund and trust budget. Unit has undergone several name changes: Vice President in Charge of Business and Finance (1935-1966); Vice President and Chief Financial Officer (1966-1993); Executive Vice President and Chief Financial Officer (1993- ). Includes administrative records reflecting oversight of the university's financial assets, preparation of annual budgets, fiscal policy, investments and expenditures, and various financial issues. Documentation includes topical files, university budgets, and trust fund records. Includes files of office holders Shirley Wheeler Smith, Robert P. Briggs, Wilbur K. Pierpont, James Brinkerhoff, and Farris Womack, Chandler Matthews, Robert Kasdin, and Timothy Slottow.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
213 linear feet
1 oversize folders
51 oversize volumes
The initial bulk of this record group (Donor No. 4094 ) was transferred in 1984. Several periodic additions have been made, including a major transfer in 2000.
The Vice President and Chief Financial Officer records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Vice President and Chief Financial Officer record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 76
Executive Officer Records -- Boxes 140-142, 144-230
Along with the president and provost, the Vice President and Chief Financial Officer shares responsibility for the general management of the University of Michigan by providing leadership for strategic initiatives and policy development. The Board of Regents has delegated to the Vice President and Chief Financial Officer broad authority to manage financial affairs. With a 2002/2003 budget of over $3.6 billion, the University of Michigan is not only an academic institution but also a major public corporation. This was not always the case.
Throughout most of the nineteenth century, business operations at the University of Michigan involved rather simple bookkeeping procedures. Expenses consisted of salaries for professors and the costs of books for the library and janitorial services. A university secretary and a treasurer handled most of these financial matters. At the turn of the century, as the physical plant increased in size and as university functions expanded with the addition of many new units, the need for more sophisticated and centralized control of university finances became obvious.
In 1908, Shirley Wheeler Smith was appointed Secretary of the university. Smith gradually extended centralized control over financial operations. In 1910, a new position of superintendent of buildings and grounds was established. A full-time purchasing agent was appointed in 1911. Both of these offices reported to Smith. In 1935, Smith's broad ranging responsibilities were recognized by the Regents when he was given the title of "Vice President in Charge of Business and Finance."
By 1940, Smith supervised 75 persons and his office was responsible for all financial management of the university. Smith reported directly to the president and the Board of Regents. Responsibilities included accounting, purchasing, investments, cash management, buildings and grounds, and services such as printing, stores, housing, and utilities.
In 1945, Shirley Smith retired and was replaced by Robert P. Briggs. In that same year, the position of secretary was made a separate one and, eventually, was relocated to the president's office. After 1945, the vice president's office experienced constant reorganization. Caused by the ever-expanding volume of university business, the reorganizations were intended to draw clear lines of administrative responsibility. In 1945, the Offices of Plant Superintendent and Non-academic Personnel were created. Also in 1945, several operating units were established as self-sustaining units such as the departments of printing, binding, and laundry. In 1947, the first full-time university attorney was named.
In 1951, Robert Briggs resigned and was succeeded by Wilbur K. Pierpont. Pierpont had previously been Professor of Accounting at the University of Michigan and the University Controller. During the 1950s, the continued rapid expansion of the university led to a continuing series of organizational and staff changes to respond to these new and larger responsibilities of the business and financial staff. The whirlwind of change begun under the Briggs administration continued unabated under Pierpont. The Controller's Office and the Purchasing Department underwent major restructuring. A new parking operations unit was established in 1955 and an internal audit unit was created which would be renamed University Audits in 1966.
By 1955, the North Campus development as well as other campus extensions in Ann Arbor led to the creation of the post of Assistant to the Vice President for Business and Finance. This position was first held by John McKevitt. Another assistantship, with responsibilities for general and budget services, was added in 1967 and was filled by Harlan J. Mulder, who served until 1987. When McKevitt left in 1969 his position was not filled until William Sturgis was appointed assistant in 1974. Sturgis had worked previously as an administrative assistant at the Law School and as a financial analyst in the Office of the Vice President. Sturgis was Assistant to the Vice President and Chief Financial Officer from 1974 until his retirement in 1991.
Between 1956 and 1958, the Flint and Dearborn campuses were started and business managers were appointed for both of these units. Other subsidiary units were created and placed under the authority of the vice president. In 1959, the Office of Staff Benefits was established and in 1961 the Office of Financial Analysis was organized. During the 1960s, the growth in university related litigation led to an increase in the university attorney's staff and to the naming of a University General Counsel in 1970. Many other offices reporting to the vice president underwent similar growth or changes in function or reporting relationship. The result was a highly complex organizational structure.
In 1976, Wilbur Pierpont resigned as vice president to return to teaching and was replaced by James F. Brinkerhoff as Vice President and Chief Financial Officer. The change in the title of the office had occurred, previously, in 1966. Brinkerhoff had been Director of the Plant Extension Department and then Associate Vice President and Director of Business Operations. Through the later part of the 1970s and into the 1980s, the rapid organizational changes of the previous years slackened and the office's structure appeared more stable. Perhaps the most important challenge faced by the Brinkerhoff administration was overseeing construction of the new university hospital in the 1980s. Careful monitoring of the financial aspects of this complicated project helped to assure the successful completion of the hospital in 1985.
In 1988, James Brinkerhoff resigned and was succeeded by Farris W. Womack. Prior to coming to the University of Michigan, Womack had been Controller for the State of North Carolina and had held academic and administrative appointments at the University of North Carolina and at the University of Arkansas. Womack announced his retirement in 1996. During Womack's tenure the office was renamed as Executive Vice President and Chief Financial Officer. Chandler Matthews served as interim CFO during 1997 prior to the appointment of Robert Kasdin as Executive Vice President and Chief Financial Officer. Kasdin resigned in 2002 and was succeeded by Timothy Slottow.
The history of the office of the Vice President and Chief Financial Officer is a history of nearly constant reorganization and name changes for subordinate offices. Researchers who would like more detail regarding this history should consult The University of Michigan: An Encyclopedic Survey(volume I, pages 269-280 and volume VI, pages 1-108) for changes occurring up to 1975.
Chief Financial Officers of the University of Michigan
Vice President and Secretary of the University
1930-1935 Shirley W. Smith
Vice President in Charge of Business and Finance
1935-1945 Shirley W. Smith
1945-1951 Robert P. Briggs
1951-1966 Wilbur K. Pierpont
Vice President and Chief Financial Officer
1966-1971 Wilbur K. Pierpont
1977-1987 James F. Brinkerhoff
1988-1993 Farris W. Womack
Executive Vice President and Chief Financial Officer
1993-1996 Farris W. Womack
1997 Chandler Matthews (Interim)
1997-2002 Robert Kasdin
2002-2003 Timothy Slottow (Interim )
2003-2014 Timothy Slottow
2014- Doug Strong (Interim )
Summary Contents List
Central Topical Files, 1929-1997
1929-1977 -- Boxes 1-25, 204
1963-1988 -- Boxes 59-65
1925-1989 -- Boxes 67-75
1937-1999 (bulk 1980-1991), -- Boxes 85-139
1951-1997 (bulk 1982-1997) -- Boxes 140-142
1957-2003 (bulk 1992-2002) -- Boxes 160-189
1960-2006 -- Boxes 205-215
Supplemental Files
1957-2001 -- Boxes 190-203
1979-2004 (bulk 1998-2003) -- Boxes 215-222
Assistant to the Vice President and Chief Financial Officer
Topical Files
1940-1988 -- Boxes 77-84
1979-2005 (bulk 1998-2003) -- Boxes 222-230
Associate Vice President for Finance
Topical Files
1996-2006 (bulk 1998-2003) -- Boxes 144-159
University Budgets, Accounts and Reports
Annual University Budgets, 1909/10-1946/47 (Oversize, list after Box 25)
University Hospital Budgets, 1951/52-1970/71 (Box 204 and Oversize, list after Box 25)
Project (Trust Fund) Budget, 1948/49-1977/78 -- Boxes 34-50, and Outsize)
Photographs
Photographs of Financial Officers -- Box 143
Photographs of Official Ceremonies and Events -- Box 230
Measuring 230 linear feet, 1 oversize folder, and 51 oversize volumes, the records of the Vice President and Chief Financial Officer document the fiscal history of the university beginning from 1909. At least since the 1950s the vice president has taken responsibility for the creation of university policy in areas requiring special fiscal knowledge as well as for the preparation of the university's general fund and trust budgets. Other activities, such as policing actual expenditures or the day to day operations of specific service units within the university reporting to the vice president, have been delegated to subordinate offices.
Reflecting this division of responsibility, the records of the vice president document major fiscal issues facing the university and the preparation of the university's annual budgets. Some of the records are office files. However, the office also retained many key bound financial documents including an official set of the university's annual budgets.
The records are organized into six series: Central Topical Files; Supplemental Files; Assistant to the Vice President and Chief Financial Officer; Associate Vice President for Finance; University Budgets, Accounts and Reports; and Photographs. Most series are further divided into several subseries, reflecting different accessions. There is considerable overlap in date span of the topical files of the Vice President and Chief Financial Officer. Files created by one Vice President were sometimes retained for use by his successor(s) and transferred at a much later date than the bulk of his records.
Subjects:
Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy.; Michigan Council of State College Presidents.; University of Michigan--Administration.; University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Finance.; University of Michigan--Flint.; University of Michigan--Gifts and loans.; University of Michigan. Hospitals.; University of Michigan--Student housing.; University of Michigan--Planning.; University of Michigan. Press.; University of Michigan--Students--Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; University of Michigan. Vice-President and Chief Financial Officer.; University of Michigan. Willow Run Laboratories.; Willow Run Airport (Mich.); Disinvestment--South Africa.
Contributors:
Briggs, Robert Peter, 1903-; Brinkerhoff, James F.; Kasdin, Robert A.; Matthews, Chandler W.; Pierpont, Wilbur K., 1914-; Slottow, Timothy P.; Sturgis, William S.; Womack, Farris W.
- Central Topical Files, 1929-2003
  - 1929-1977, 1955-1975
    The 1929-1977 Topical File (1984 accession, boxes 1-25), includes records dating from 1929 to 1977, however, the bulk of this material dates between 1955 and 1975. The 25 linear feet of material is arranged in one alphabet according to subject headings devised by the office. This subseries generally documents the creation of policy in areas requiring financial expertise, such as investment or insurance, as well as the implementation of other university policies through the expenditure of funds. Major subject headings include: Budget, Capital Outlay Requests, Compensation, Fees, Gifts, Hospital, Indirect Costs, Insurance, Investment, Personnel, Plant Extension, Staff Benefits, and Willow Run. Several audits of the university and its hospital published by the state auditor are found within the vice president's records. They are located under the heading "Auditor General (State of Michigan)."
    - Acquisition of W.K. Goss property (3115 Glacier Way), 1966 (Box 1)
    - Administrative Systems
      - Data Systems Center
        - 1971-1972 (Box 1)
        - 1974-1976 (Box 1)
      - General
        - 1972 (Box 1)
        - 1974-1975 (Box 1)
        - 1976-1977 (Box 1)
      - Management Information System-Quality Assurance, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
      - Security of data, 1974-1976 (Box 1)
    - Affirmative Action [see also "Civil Rights"]
      - Business and Finance Offices, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
      - General
        - 1969-1976 (Box 1)
        - 1976 (Box 1)
      - Varner, Nellie, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - Afro-American, Center for, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - Alumni Association/Alumnae Council, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - Alumni Retirement Housing, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
    - American Council on Education, College and University Reporter, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    - American Institute of Indian Studies, 1969-1973 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor
      - Police and Fire Services to University, 1971 (Box 1)
      - Public (low income) Housing, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
      - Public Schools (School Board)
        - 1963-1969 (Box 1)
        - 1970 (Box 1)
        - 1971 (Box 1)
        - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
      - Relation with University (Box 2)
        - 1929-1939 (Box 2)
        - 1940-1955 (Box 2)
        - 1955-1957, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - 1956-1965 (Box 2)
        - 1967-1970 (Box 2)
        - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
        - 1973-1974 (Box 2)
        - 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    - Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy (AURA)
      - 1972-1973 (Box 2)
      - 1973-1974, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 1975, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 1976, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Athletics
      - Board in Control
        - Audited Financial Statements, 1961-1970 (Box 2)
        - Reports of, 1962-1971 (Box 2)
      - General
        - 1968-1971 (Box 3)
        - 1973 (Box 3)
        - 1973-1979 (Box 3)
      - Recreation Facilities
        - 1968-1972 (Box 3)
        - 1973 (Box 3)
      - Women, 1973-1974 (Box 3)
    - Auditor General (State of Michigan)
      - 1962-1965 (Box 3)
      - 1965-1966
        - Indirect Cost Rates (Box 3)
        - Report (Box 3)
      - 1971-1973 (Box 3)
      - Hospital, 1971-1974 (Box 3)
      - 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Audits for Regents
      - 1968-1969 (Box 3)
      - 1971-1976 (Box 3)
    - Audits, Outside, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
    - Barbour, Levi (Gifts and Miscellaneous), 1964-1969 (Box 3)
    - Barbour-Waterman Gym
      - 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Beaumont Hospital, 1968-1976 (Box 3)
    - Bentley, Alvin M., 1966-1971 (Box 3)
    - Big Ten Business Officers, 1975 (Box 3)
    - Biological Station
      - 1961-1972 (Box 4)
      - 1973 (Box 4)
      - 1974 (Box 4)
    - Bookstore
      - 1958-1969 (Box 4)
      - 1970-1974 (Box 4)
    - Branch Campus Operations, 1970-1972 (Box 4)
    - Brown, Robert, 1966-1974 (Box 4)
    - Bruggeman Property (Adrian, Michigan), 1970-1971 (Box 4)
    - Budget
      - Annual
        - 1939-1947 (Box 4)
        - 1948-1950 (Box 4)
        - 1966-1967 (Box 4)
        - 1967-1968
          - Additional Appropriations (Box 4)
          - Supporting Material (Box 4)
        - 1968-1969 (Box 4)
        - 1969-1970 (Box 4)
        - 1970-1971
          - Actual Fiscal Reports (Box 4)
          - Commission on Resource Allocation (Box 4)
          - Cost Reduction (Box 4)
        - 1971-1972
          - Final Fiscal Reports (Box 4)
          - General, 2 folders (Box 5)
          - Legislative and Budget Hearings (Box 5)
        - 1972-1973
          - Commission on Resource Allocation (Box 5)
          - Fiscal Reports (Box 5)
          - General (Box 5)
          - Legislative Material (Box 5)
          - Long Range Planning Committee (Box 5)
          - Program Evaluation Committee (Box 5)
        - 1973-1974
          - Budget Priorities Committee (Box 5)
          - Formula (Box 5)
          - General, 2 folders (Box 5)
          - Legislative Material (Box 5)
        - 1974-1975
          - Cost Reductions (Box 5)
          - General (Box 5)
          - Long Range Planning Committee (Box 5)
          - Priorities (Box 5)
          - State Appropriation (Box 5)
          - Year End Closing (Box 5)
          - Year End Fiscal Report (Box 5)
        - 1975-1976
          - Budget Priorities Committee (Box 6)
          - Cash Flow and State Allotment (Box 6)
          - Cutbacks, January 1975 (Box 6)
          - Fiscal Year Change by State (Box 6)
          - General (Box 6)
          - Long Range Planning Committee (Box 6)
          - Salary and Wage Program, 1975-1976 (Box 6)
            (includes 1973-1974)
          - Total Return Fund (Box 6)
          - Year End Closing, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Balances Carried Forward, 1964-1974 (Box 6)
      - Communications to Robben Fleming, 1972-1976 (Box 6)
      - Comparison of General Fund Budget to Actual Expenses
        - 1960-1961 (Box 6)
        - 1969-1970 to 1975-1976 (Box 6)
      - Cost Reductions, 1964-1970 (Box 6)
    - Budget and Planning, Office of, 1971-1975 (Box 6)
    - Building and Land Improvements
      - 1967-1970 (Box 6)
      - 1970-1974 (Box 6)
    - Budget Team, 1976-1978; 2 folders (Box 204)
    - Buildings under Study, 1960-1976 (Box 7)
    - Camp, Speech Improvement, 1947-1951 (Box 7)
    - Capital Outlay Requests (State)
      - 1943-1945 (Box 7)
      - 1946-1955 (Box 7)
      - 1954-1955 (Box 7)
      - 1955-1956 (Box 7)
      - 1956-1957 (Box 7)
      - 1957-1958 (Box 7)
      - 1958-1959 (Box 7)
      - 1959-1960 (Box 7)
      - 1960-1961 (Box 7)
      - 1961-1962 (Box 7)
        (5 year study)
      - 1962-1963, 1963-1964 (Box 7)
      - 1963-1965 (Box 7)
      - 1965-1966
        - Act 124, 2 folders (Box 7)
        - General, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - 1966-1967 (Box 8)
      - 1967-1968
        - Act 124 (Box 8)
        - General (Box 8)
      - 1968-1970 (Box 8)
      - 1971-1972 (Box 8)
      - 1972-1973, 1973-1974 (Box 8)
      - 1974-1975 (Box 8)
    - Capital Outlay Requests (Federal), 1961-1967 (Box 8)
    - Carnegie Commission and Corporation, 1970-1976 (Box 8)
    - Central Association College and University Business Officers (CACUBO), 1949-1955 (Box 8)
    - Cheever House, 1945-1968 (Box 8)
    - Child Care, 1974-1975 (Box 8)
    - Civil Defense, 1957-1969 (Box 8)
    - Civil Rights [see also "Affirmative Action"]
      - Affirmative Action-Architects and Contractors, 1968-1973 (Box 8)
      - File Review for Sex Discrimination, 1971-1973 (Box 8)
      - Grievance Procedure, 1971-1973 (Box 8)
      - LS&A Deanship, 1975 (Box 8)
      - Minority Students, 1971-1973 (Box 8)
    - Climax Molybdenum Company, 1963-1984 (Box 9)
    - Community Medicine Program, 1972-1974 (Box 9)
    - Compensation
      - General, 1971-1973 (Box 9)
      - Program, 1974-1975 (Box 9)
      - Salary Policy-Year Round Operation, 1974-1975 (Box 9)
      - Surveys
        - Inter-Institutional, 1964 (Box 9)
        - Inter-Institutional, 1976-1977 (Box 9)
        - University of Michigan, 1976-1977 (Box 9)
        - University of Michigan, 1976 (Box 9)
      - Wage-Price Freeze, 1971-1973 (Box 9)
    - Computing Center, 1972-1973 (Box 9)
    - Conductron Property, 1970-1971 (Box 9)
    - Cost-Analysis Manual, 1973-1976 (Box 9)
    - Cost Studies, 1963-1976 (Box 9)
    - Costs, Student Level, 1961-1962 (Box 9)
    - Council of State College Presidents-Division of Business Officers, 1952-1963 (Box 9)
    - Cudlip, William B., 1967-1972 (Box 9)
    - Cummer Gun Collection and Fund, 1969-1974 (Box 9)
    - Dearborn
      - Campus
        - 1963-1970 (Box 9)
        - 1971 (Box 9)
        - 1973 (Box 9)
        - 1974 (Box 9)
      - Fairlane Mansion, 1961-1973 (Box 9)
    - Development Steering Committee, 1976-1977 (Box 10)
    - Energy Conservation, 1973 (Box 10)
    - Engineering, Capital Campaign of College, 1972-1973 (Box 10)
    - Environmental Research Institute of Michigan [see also "Willow Run Laboratories"], 1971-1973 (Box 10)
    - Fees
      - Application, 1969-1971 (Box 10)
      - Deferred Tuition Plan, 1970-1973 (Box 10)
      - General
        - 1967, 1972-1973 (Box 10)
        - 1973-1974 (Box 10)
        - 1974-1975 (Box 10)
      - Price Freeze, 1973 (Box 10)
      - Residency, 1971-1973 (Box 10)
      - Structure (Committee on Fee Structure), 1973-1977; 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Studies, 1929-1958 (Box 10)
    - Financial Report, 1972-1974 (Box 10)
    - Financing Buildings
      - 1962-1965 (Box 10)
      - Legal Opinion, 1966 (Box 10)
      - 1966-1967 (Box 10)
      - 1968 (Box 10)
      - 1969-1970 (Box 10)
      - 1971-1972 (Box 10)
    - Financial Crisis, 1959 (Box 10)
    - Fisk University, 1974 (Box 10)
    - Flint (Box 11)
      - Budget Statements, 1968/1969-1970/1971 (Box 204)
      - Campus
        - 1952-1955 (Box 11)
        - 1962-1967 (Box 11)
        - 1968 (Box 11)
        - 1971-1972 (Box 11)
        - 1974 (Box 11)
        - 1975-1976 (Box 11)
      - Computers, 1974-1976 (Box 11)
      - Riverfront Campus Project
        - Communications to Regents, 1970-1973 (Box 11)
        - General
          - 1972 (Box 11)
          - 1973 (Box 11)
        - Quarterly Status Reports, 1973-1976 (Box 11)
        - Studies, 1972-1973; 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Urban Renewal Program, 1968-1970 (Box 11)
    - Foundation, University (Idea for), 1968-1969 (Box 11)
    - Fraternities and Sororities, 1968-1974 (Box 11)
    - Fund Raising, 1968 (Box 11)
    - Gift Receiving Policies, 1957-1968; 1967-1973; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Gifts
      - Pooled Life Income Fund (Box 12)
        - 1957-1967 (Box 12)
        - 1968-1973 (Box 12)
        - 1973-1976 (Box 12)
      - State Tax Credit, 1968-1974 (Box 12)
    - Goebel, Paul G., 1965-1973 (Box 12)
    - Green Hills Foundation, 1975-1976 (Box 12)
    - Health Professions Student Loan Program, 1963-1965 (Box 12)
    - Health Research Facilities
      - 1957-1962 (Box 12)
      - 1961-1965 (Box 12)
    - Health Service (Student), 1972-1973 (Box 12)
    - Herbst Properties and Fund, 1960-1968 (Box 12)
    - Higher Education